<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0-subset Scilab" xml:lang="en" xml:id="interferometry_gui"><info><pubdate>February 2004</pubdate></info><refnamediv><refname>interferometry_gui</refname><refpurpose>Graphical User
      Interface (GUI) for SIP functions</refpurpose></refnamediv>
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   <refsection><title>Description</title>
   
      <para>
 This is a quick start guide: first of all, this GUI was  written to make 
tests in the photonic field, which means  you'll find many 
functions related to laser images. </para>
   
      <para>
 As it is highly customizable, you can adapt it easily to  your needs. </para>
   
      <para>
 Here is a description of a few experiments and pictures:  
</para>

      <para>
1) laser1.jpg is a picture of a laser beam magnified by a microscope 
objective X10 and filtered by a pinhole of a  few microns (=spatial filter).
Operation &gt; Profiles show the intensity profiles.
LaserBeam &gt; Find Gaussian Profiles allows modelling of  these profiles by a
 gaussian curve (laser beam should have  a gaussian profile). 
The beam waist can be deducted from  these values.
The laser speckle can be smoothed by one (or several)  median filtering(s) found in Operations: this filter  removes the high-frequency noise. </para>
   
      <para>
 2) speckle1.png and speckle2.png are 2 images of an experiment in speckle interferometry: 
a Michelson interferometer is created but the 1st mirror is replaced by 
a rugged  metallic piece and the second one is replaced by a metallic rule.  
A CCD Camera saves a first image.  The rule is bent. 
The Camera take a second picture.  
Try, Open &gt; speckle1.png then Operations &gt; substract 2  images 
(absolute value).  
Fringes appear: between 2 dark fringes, the rule has moved  from a 
distance equal to the light wavelength/2 (here,  633/2=316.5 nm).  
Normalization, filtering can help better visualization of  the fringes. </para>
   
      <para>
 3) pyramide_wrapped.jpg is what is called a phased image:  
it was obtained by projecting fringes on an object then on  a 
reference plane.  
The goal is to modelize the object in 3D. 
Operations &gt;  Profiles show that luminance is somewhat proportional to  altitude, 
but each time its value reach 255, there's a  jump and the luminance 
restart from zero.  
The phase unwrapping process is intended to remove these  jumps.  
PhasedImages &gt; Unwrap linearly can do it with a very good  quality image (like pyramide_wrapped.jpg).  
A more complex algorithm is used by Unwrap by path following: 
it can unwrap more difficult images. 
You can test  with the merit function called Variance: it's usually the  best choice. 
Be a bit patient when launching those functions: it takes  some time (about 2 min on a recent computer). </para>
   
   </refsection>

   
   <refsection><title>Authors</title><simplelist type="vert">
      
      <member> Jocelyn DRUEL &lt;jocelyn.druel1@libertysurf.fr&gt; </member>
   
   </simplelist></refsection>


   <refsection><title>Availability</title>
The latest version of the Scilab Image Processing toolbox can be found at
<para>
         http://siptoolbox.sourceforge.net
      </para>

   </refsection>

   
   <refsection><title>See Also</title><simplelist type="inline">
      
      <member> 
         <link linkend="unwrapp">unwrapp</link> 
      </member>
      
      <member> 
         <link linkend="unwrapl">unwrapl</link> 
      </member>
      
      <member> 
         <link linkend="improfile">improfile</link> 
      </member>
   
   </simplelist></refsection>

</refentry>